Guide to the Arthur F. Burns Papers, 1911-2005 and undated, bulk 1940-1987 RL.00179
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Arthur F. Burns papers
1911-2005 and undated, bulk 1940-1987
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Burns, Arthur F., 1904-1987
RL.00179
18.5 Linear Feet approximately 2,675 items
2.6 Gigabytes
Arthur Frank Burns was an Austrian-born economist, policy maker, and diplomat; chair of U.S. Federal Reserve Board from 1970-1978 and economic advisor for six U.S. presidencies. These papers cover the years 1911 through 2005. The bulk of the material was created between 1940 and 1987 and pertains to Burns's career as an economic advisor, particularly to Republican administrations, as the chair of the Federal Reserve, and as ambassador to Germany. The collection is arranged into seven series: Correspondence, Honors and Awards, Journals, Personal Papers, Photographs, Print Materials, and Research and Teaching. Topics of interest in this collection include but are not limited to: the United States economic system and fiscal policies; the Federal Reserve Board and related committees; recessions, unemployment, and inflation; the world economy and finance; the U.S. presidency during the time period; the Nixon presidency in particular, including the Watergate affair; presidential campaigns and elections; and U.S. diplomacy. There is a limited amount of research and teaching material, chiefly from the 1920s-1930s. The most significant component of the collection is the correspondence between Arthur Burns and Presidents Eisenhower, Nixon, Kennedy, Ford, Carter, Reagan, and George H. W. Bush, as well as substantive exchanges with economists Milton Friedman and Wesley Clair Mitchell. There are a few letters in German, French, and Russian.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. However, originals of high-value correspondence are restricted except for use under direct staff supervision. Patrons are requested to use either CD-ROM surrogates of selected letters or photocopies of originals in boxes 1-3.
Electronic records in this collection have been migrated to a library server and digital use copies can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access, please contact Research Services before coming to use these records.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Arthur F. Burns Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from 2006-2012.
Biographical Note
Arthur Frank Burns, economist, policy maker and diplomat, was born into an Austro-Hungarian Jewish family in Stanislau, Galicia (now part of Ukraine) in 1904. His family immigrated to the United States in 1914 and settled in New Jersey. In 1925 Burns received A.B. and A.M. degrees in economics from Columbia University. He worked under renowned economist Wesley Clair Mitchell and received his Ph.D. in economics from Columbia in 1934. Between 1926 and 1944 he taught at Columbia and Rutgers. He was named full professor at Rutgers University in 1943. Burns's economic thought was inspired by Keynes, yet he believed that the Keynesian model was simplistic and totalistic as, according to Burns, each industry had its own cycle, hence government intervention should be taken selectively and upon detailed statistical analysis. Burns joined the National Bureau of Economics as Research Associate in 1930; in later years he served as the Director of Research (1945-1953), President (1957-1967), and Chairman (1967-1968) of this institution.
Burns's political involvement with the Republican Party began with his support for Eisenhower in the 1952 election. Burns acted as the Chairman of the Council of Advisors to the President (1953-1956), Chairman of the Cabinet Committee on Small Business (1956), and as member of U.S. Advisory Council on Social Security Financing (1957-1958).
Burns was also an economic advisor to Nixon's 1968 presidential campaign and acted as the White House economic advisor from 1969-1970. He was appointed Chairman of the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve on Jan. 31, 1970, and held the position until March 1978. Meanwhile, he also served as the Head of the Committee on Interest and Dividends (1971-1974), a committee founded as part of Nixon's Economic Stabilization Program; as the U.S. Alternate Governor to the International Monetary Fund (1973-1978); and as a member of Emergency Loan Guarantee Board (1971-1978). The Nixon administration took over an economy in crisis, and Burns proposed a recovery program, which in the early days seemed to be effective. This period and Burns's reactions to its crises are well-documented in the correspondence and personal journals found in this collection. Between 1977-1981 and 1985-1987, Burns served as a distinguished scholar at the American Enterprise Institute for Public Policy, where he taught and wrote. In 1981, Ronald Reagan appointed him U.S. Ambassador to the Federal Republic of Germany, a position he held until May 16, 1985. Burns passed away on June 26, 1987 in Baltimore, Maryland. Burns's theories have inspired many economists, including his renowned student Milton Friedman.
Selected Publications:
1934 Production Trends in the United States Since 1870. New York: National Bureau of Economic Research
1946 Measuring Business Cycles. New York: National Bureau of Economic Research, with Wesley Mitchell
1952 Wesley Clair Mitchell: the Economic Scientist. New York: National Bureau of Economic Research
1957 Frontiers of Economic Knowledge. Princeton: University of Princeton Press Prosperity without Inflation. Buffalo: Smith, Keynes & Marshall
1967 Full Employment: Guideposts and Economic Stability. Washington D.C.: American Enterprise Institute for Public Policy Research, with Paul Samuelson
1969 Business Cycle in a Changing World. New York: Columbia University Press
1978 Reflections of an Economic Policy Maker: Speeches and Congressional Statements, 1969-1978. Washington D.C.: American Enterprise Institute for Public Policy Research
General
Some of the autographed original letters were photographed with a digital camera before the collection was acquired by the library. Digital image files were provided to the library on CD-Rom. Files from those CD-Roms were migrated to a library server. To request access to these electronic copies, please contact Research Services in the Rubenstein Library before coming to use this collection.
Collection Overview
The Arthur Frank Burns Papers cover the years 1911 through 2005. The bulk of the material was created from 1940 to 1987 and pertains to Burns's career as an economic advisor, particularly to Republican administrations, as the chair of the Federal Reserve, and as ambassador to Germany. The collection is arranged into seven series: Correspondence, Honors and Awards, Journals, Personal Papers, Photographs, Print Materials, and Research and Teaching. There are also oversize materials housed at the end of the collection. Topics of interest in this collection include but are not limited to: the United States economic system and fiscal policies; the Federal Reserve Board and related committees; recessions, unemployment, and inflation; the world economy and finance; the U.S. presidency during the time period; the Nixon presidency in particular, including the Watergate affair; presidential campaigns and elections; and diplomacy. There is a small amount of research and teaching material, chiefly from the 1920s-1930s. The most significant component of the collection is the correspondence between Arthur Burns and Presidents Eisenhower, Nixon, Kennedy, Ford, Carter, Reagan, and George H. W. Bush, as well as substantial exchanges with economists Milton Friedman and Wesley Clair Mitchell.
The most substantial and notable papers are found in the Correspondence Series, which contains letters and memoranda written from 1911-1997 both to and from Burns and/or his wife, Helen. The series is organized into three subseries, Correspondence by Individual, Correspondence by Topic, and Correspondence to Mrs. Helen Burns. The majority of the exchanges in the first subseries are letters written to or by presidents or vice presidents (Dwight Eisenhower, John F. Kennedy, Richard Nixon, Jimmy Carter, Ronald Reagan, George H. W. Bush, Spiro Agnew, Hubert Humphrey, and Nelson Rockefeller). Burns's correspondence with presidents Eisenhower and Nixon is particularly extensive and reveals the making of crucial policy decisions. Also included is Burns's correspondence with economists Wesley Clair Mitchell, Milton Friedman, and George Stigler. This subseries is organized alphabetically by correspondent and then chronologically.
The Correspondence by Topic subseries contains letters and attachments primarily related to Burns's work in academia, politics, and the private sector. Finally, the Correspondence to Mrs. Helen Burns subseries contains letters written by prominent figures such as Richard Nixon, Ronald Reagan, and Mamie Eisenhower to Burns's wife, Helen, both during his life and after his death.
High-value correspondence, including originals signed by presidents and some other notable correspondents, are separately stored and restricted to use except under direct staff supervision. Photocopies of these original manuscripts have been made for researcher use. Other letters signed by mechanical means have not been photocopied, but they are filed with the photocopies of original letters.
The other series house papers and memorabilia documenting Burns' career, including photocopies of two handwritten journals (1969-1974) kept by Burns during the Nixon Administration; several folders of early research and teaching materials; honors and awards received by Burns; personal correspondence, clippings, and other materials; lectures, speeches, and articles from Burns's career as economist and ambassador; photographs of Burns, his wife Helen, and political figures and celebrities attending events; publicity items such as news clippings, interviews, and articles about Burns; and program materials for the Arthur F. Burns Fellowship, an exchange program for German and U.S. media professionals. Further description available at the series level in this collection guide.
The great majority of the Burns papers are in English, but there are roughly ten items in German and a few items in French and Russian (Cyrillic script).
Related Material
Arthur F. Burns Papers
Gerald R. Ford Library
Economists' Papers Project (Collection of notable economists' papers includes many individuals who served U.S. presidential administrations in various capacities.)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
General
National security classified materials were reviewed and declassified by the Information Security Oversight Office of the National Archives in 2015. Declassified documents are clearly marked as such.
Recessions -- United States; Presidents -- United States -- Correspondence; Watergate Affair, 1972-1974; Unemployment -- Effect of inflation on -- United States; Fiscal policy -- United States; Elections -- United States -- History; Monetary policy -- United States; Inflation (Finance) -- United States; Currency question -- United States; Ambassadors -- United States; Economists -- United States; Economists -- Correspondence; United States -- Politics and government -- 1945-1989; United States -- Economic conditions -- 1945-; United States -- History -- 1945-; Audiocassettes; CD-ROMs; Diaries; United States -- Foreign policy; Photographs; Machine-readable records; United States -- Economic policy; Burns, Arthur F. (Arthur Frank), 1904-1987; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994; Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System (U.S.); Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969; Ford, Gerald R., 1913-2006; Bush, George, 1924-2018; Carter, Jimmy, 1924-; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963; Mitchell, Wesley C. (Wesley Clair), 1874-1948; Friedman, Milton, 1912-2006; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973
- Correspondence, 1911-1997 and undated, bulk 1940-1987, 5 boxes; 347 electronic files
  Scope and Contents note
  The correspondence is organized into three subseries. The Correspondence by Individual Subseries contains correspondence and memoranda between Burns and presidents, vice-presidents, politicians, and prominent economists. The Correspondence by Topic subseries contains letters and attachments primarily related to Burns' work in academia, politics, and the private sector. Finally, the Correspondence to Mrs. Helen Burns subseries contains letters written by figures such as Richard Nixon, Ronald Reagan, and Mamie Eisenhower to Burns's wife, Helen, both during his life and after his death.
  Although high-value correspondence can be accessed in several formats, the papers housed in boxes 1-3 are the only complete record of exchanges. These boxes contain photocopies of high-value correspondence along with their original attachments, originals of other correspondence (including originals signed by mechanical means), and original onion-skin paper copies of Burns's out-going correspondence. Originals of high-value correspondence, without the corresponding attachments, are housed separately in boxes 13 and 15, and are closed to use.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Some of the letters from notable correspondents were imaged with a digital camera and provided to the library on CD-Roms. Files from those CD-Roms were migrated to a library server, but not all of the correspondence and attachments are represented.
  - Correspondence by Individual, 1911-1985, bulk 1953-1981
    Organized alphabetically by correspondent and then chronologically, the bulk of this subseries documents Burns's work with several presidential administrations. Correspondents include Dwight D. Eisenhower, John F. Kennedy, Richard Nixon, Jimmy Carter, Ronald Reagan, George H. W. Bush, Spiro Agnew, Nelson Rockefeller, and Hubert Humphrey. The subseries also includes correspondence with his mentor, Wesley Clair Mitchell, and with his students, economists Milton Friedman and George Stigler. Burns's correspondence with presidents Eisenhower and Nixon constitute the most significant part of the subseries. These exchanges cover domestic economic matters such as recession, monetary and fiscal policies to regulate inflation and unemployment; international political and economic matters; and domestic political issues such as elections and party politics.
    - Moses Abramovitz, 1942 and undated, 2 letters
      Abramovitz's correspondence to Burns discusses the editing of Abramovitz's monograph, his impressions of Washington, and the work of the War Planning Board.
      - 1942 Apr. 5 (Box 1)
      - Undated (Box 1)
    - Spiro Agnew, 1972-1973, 3 letters
      Agnew's correspondence to Burns consists of routine notes expressing thanks for Burns's support and for having sent materials.
      - 1972 Aug. 11 (Box 1)
      - 1972 Dec. 13 (Box 1)
      - 1973 Oct. 25 (Box 1)
    - James A. Baker III, 1981-1985, 2 letters
      Baker's correspondence to Burns consists of routine notes expressing thanks for Burns's support and advice.
      - 1981 Sept. 29 (Box 1)
      - 1985 Feb. 20 (Box 1)
    - George H. W. Bush, 1979-1987, 12 letters
      Bush's correspondence to Burns consists of routine notes expressing thanks for Burns's support and for having sent materials. Barbara Bush's handwritten well wishes are affixed to one note.
      - 1979 Sept. 10 (Box 1)
      - 1980 June 23 (Box 1)
      - 1980 Aug. 4 (Box 1)
      - 1980 Nov. 5 (Box 1)
        Re: Congratulations from Burns to Bush upon becoming Vice President-elect.
      - 1980 Nov. 15 (Box 1)
      - 1981 Feb. 3 (Box 1)
      - 1981 May 5 (Box 1)
      - 1982 Feb. 6 (Box 1)
      - 1983 Mar. 2 (Box 1)
      - 1983 June 30 (Box 1)
      - 1983 July 30 (Box 1)
      - 1987 June 22 (Box 1)
    - Jimmy Carter, 1976-1981, 3 folders
      Burns continued to be the Chairman of the Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve Board during the first year of the Carter administration. This correspondence documents Dr. Burns's work with the new administration especially on the matter of tax reform, along with budgetary issues and policies regarding OPEC. Burns presented his resignation to Jimmy Carter in January 1978. Included in the collection is a January 13, 1978 letter in which Carter accepts Burns's and expresses his appreciation of Burns's leadership of the Federal Reserve over the past eight years. The letters after January 1978 address non-economic issues such as Burns's receipt of the America's Democratic Legacy Award of the Anti-Defamation League and Carter's appreciation of Burns's support for his efforts in human rights. Two letters from Rosalynn Carter are also included.
      - From Carter to Burns, 1976-1981, 14 letters
        - 1976 Nov. 8 (Box 1)
        - 1976 Nov. 26 (Box 1)
        - 1977 Apr. 12 (Box 1)
        - 1977 May 22 (Box 1)
        - 1977 Sept. 20 (Box 1)
        - 1977 Oct. 19 (Box 1)
        - 1977 Dec. 12 (Box 1)
          From Rosalynn Carter to Burns.
        - 1977 Dec. 28 (Box 1)
        - 1977 Dec. 28 (Box 1)
        - 1978 Jan. 13 (Box 1)
          Re: Burns's resignation as Chairman.
        - 1978 Feb. 2 (Box 1)
          Executive order appointing Burns Acting Chairman.
        - 1978 Feb. 6 (Box 1)
        - 1978 May 18 (Box 1)
        - 1981 Mar. 3 (Box 1)
        - 1982 Oct. 29 (Box 1)
      - From Burns to Carter, 1976-1978, 33 letters
        - 1976 Sept. 24 (Box 1)
          News clipping from The New York Times re: Role of Federal Reserve in Carter-Ford debate.
        - 1976 Nov. 3 (Box 1)
        - 1976 Nov. 12 (Box 1)
        - 1976 Nov. 23 (Box 1)
        - 1977 Feb. 1 (Box 1)
          Memo re: Carter.
        - 1977 Feb. 4 (Box 1)
          Attached: Statement to House Banking Committee.
        - 1977 Feb. 23 (Box 1)
        - 1977 Feb. 28 (Box 1)
        - 1977 Mar. 2 (Box 1)
        - 1977 Mar. 8 (Box 1)
          Memo re: conversation with Carter and Mondale regarding disagreement about state of the economy and press coverage of Burns's comments during Congressional hearings.
        - 1977 Mar. 23 (Box 1)
        - 1977 Mar. 24 (Box 1)
        - 1977 Mar. 31 (Box 1)
          Attached: Memo on proposal to reduce inflation.
        - 1977 Apr. 12 (Box 1)
        - 1977 Apr. 14 (Box 1)
          Memo re: Carter attaching clipping.
        - 1977 Apr. 15 (Box 1)
          President's statement on inflation.
        - 1977 May 13 (Box 1)
        - 1977 May 15 (Box 1)
        - 1977 May 25 (Box 1)
        - 1977 June 14 (Box 1)
          Attached: Memo on conversation with Vladimir Alkhimov, 1977 June 9.
        - 1977 June 22 (Box 1)
        - 1977 July 27 (Box 1)
          Stephen S. Gardner to Burns. Attached: 3 items. Carter memo re: Civil Rights Act, 1977 July 20. Carter memo re: handicapped people, 1977 July 21. Memo from Gardner, 1977 July 26.
        - 1977 July 28 (Box 1)
        - 1977 Aug. 12 (Box 1)
        - 1977 Sept. 13 (Box 1)
        - 1977 Sept. 19 (Box 1)
        - 1977 Oct. 17 (Box 1)
        - 1977 Oct. 25 (Box 1)
        - 1977 Nov. 2 (Box 1)
        - 1977 Nov. 28 (Box 1)
        - 1977 Nov. 28 (Box 1)
        - 1978 Jan. 12 (Box 1)
        - 1978 Mar. (Box 1)
          President's remarks at swearing in of G. William Miller as Chairman of the Federal Reserve.
    - Dwight David Eisenhower, 1953-1968 and undated, 17 folders
      Burns acted as the Chairman of the Council of Advisors to the President (1953-1956), Chairman of the Cabinet Committee on Small Business (1956), and a member of U.S. Advisory Council on Social Security Financing (1957-1958) during the Eisenhower Administration. He played an especially crucial role in steering the implementation of anti-recession policies. Even after he resigned from the Council of Economic Advisors, he continued to counsel the president on economic matters.
      Topics in the correspondence include economic issues such as how to combat recession/depression and inflation, unemployment, budget planning, taxes, government expenditure, monetary policy, value of the dollar, and gold reserves. The letters also address U.S. domestic politics and international relations, such as the situation in Vietnam and Cuba and the Mutual Security Program. Burns's correspondence with Eisenhower continued after his term as the President ended in 1961; the topic of the correspondence shifts to personal notes and exchanges on general economic models and policies, evaluation of the Eisenhower period economic policies and assessment, and expresses criticism of economic, political and foreign policies of the administrations of the time.
      - From Eisenhower to Burns, 1953-1968, 182 letters
        - 1953 Apr. 1 (Box 1)
          Burns's appointment letter as Economic Advisor to the President.
        - 1953 July 15 (Box 1)
        - 1953 Aug. 8 (Box 1)
          Order appointing Burns.
        - 1953 Aug. 24 (Box 1)
          Attached: Letter from Burns to Eisenhower, 1953 Aug. 27.
        - 1953 Nov. 3 (Box 1)
        - 1953 Dec. 30 (Box 1)
        - Undated (Box 1)
          Charges Union Leaders Plot to Run Nation with handwritten note signed D addressing it to Burns.
        - 1954 Jan. 15 (Box 1)
        - 1954 Jan. 23 (Box 1)
          Memorandum for Dr. Burns. D.D. Eisenhower submits a copy of the report regarding the overall foreign economic policy of the country and expresses his concerns about the pace of Executive Departments and Agencies in proceeding with the plan in the report.
        - 1954 Feb. 1 (Box 1)
          Attached: 3 items. Memorandum signed by Eisenhower for Burns, 1954 Feb. 1, regarding the measures that the government decided to employ to fight recession and prevent serious deflation and the role Burns is expected to play. Letter from Burns to Eisenhower, 1954 Feb. 8. Letter from True D. Morse to Burns, 1954 Feb. 1, regarding agricultural sector related public projects to be implemented. Formerly classified as SECRET and declassified by the ISOO, 2015.
        - 1954 Feb. 24 (Box 1)
        - 1954 Apr. 19 (Box 1)
          Attached: Letter from Burns to Eisenhower, 1954 Apr. 16.
        - 1954 Apr. 26 (Box 1)
        - 1954 Oct. 23 (Box 1)
        - 1954 Dec. 22 (Box 1)
        - 1954 Dec. 22 (Box 1)
          Attached: 2 items. Letter from Eisenhower to Ruth Caroll, 1954 Dec. 17. Letter from Ruth Caroll to Eisenhower, undated.
        - 1954 Dec. 29 (Box 1)
        - 1955 Jan. 14 (Box 1)
        - 1955 Apr. 22 (Box 1)
        - 1955 Aug. 22 (Box 1)
        - 1955 Sept. 9 (Box 1)
        - 1955 Oct. 19 (Box 1)
          From Eisenhower's assistant to Burns.
        - 1955 Dec. 29 (Box 1)
        - 1956 Mar. 10 (Box 1)
        - 1956 Apr. 18 (Box 1)
        - 1956 Apr. 24 (Box 1)
          From Secretary of the Treasury George M. Humphrey re: automobile industry.
        - 1956 Apr. 25 (Box 1)
        - 1956 May 28 (Box 1)
        - 1956 May 31 (Box 1)
        - 1956 June 1 (Box 1)
          Attached: Letter from Edgar Newton Eisenhower to Dwight Eisenhower, 1956 May 29, regarding the issues of budget and tax reform. Contains 2 copies of attached letter.
        - 1956 June 4 (Box 1)
        - 1956 June 15 (Box 1)
        - 1956 July 14 (Box 1)
          Re: The steel strike.
        - 1956 Aug. 9 (Box 1)
        - 1956 Aug. 17 (Box 1)
          Re: Burns's meeting with Bill Martins and success in getting unanimous support for the Small Business Report.
        - 1956 Aug. 18 (Box 1)